Bruce Kellner Vassar Miller Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Bruce Kellner Vassar Miller Papers
1970-2000
Kellner, Bruce
Professor and author Bruce Kellner met the Houston-based poet Vassar Miller in 1974. This collection includes correspondence from Miller to Kellner, poems by Vassar Miller, critical essays about Vassar Miller, and a typescript of Bruce Kellner's play Swimming on Concrete
1 box; .4 linear feet
2000-006
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Vassar Miller
Vassar Miller was born in Houston in 1924, the daughter of a prominent architect. She began writing as a child, composing on a typewriter due to the cerebral palsy which affected her speech and movement. She attended the University of Houston, receiving her B.A. and M.A. in English.
In 1956, Miller published her first volume of poetry, Adam's Footprint. Her poems, most of which dealt with either her strong religious faith or her experiences as a person with a disability, were widely praised for their rigorous formality, clarity, and emotional impact. In 1961 Miller was nominated for a Pulitzer Prize for her collection Wage War on Silence. Over the course of a literary career which spanned almost forty years, Miller published ten volumes of poetry in all. An outspoken advocate for the rights and dignity of the handicapped, Miller also edited a collection of poetry and short stories about persons with disabilities titled Despite This Flesh.
Miller received many awards and accolades for her poetry in her home state. Three of her books won the annual poetry prize of the Texas Institute of Letters. In 1982 and 1988 Miller was named Poet Laureate of Texas, and in 1997 she was named to the Texas Women's Hall of Fame by the Governor's Commission for Women.
Vassar Miller died in 1998.
Bruce Kellner
Bruce Kellner is Emeritus Professor of English at Millersville University, near Lancaster, Pennsylvania. He is the author/editor of over a dozen books on literature and several plays. His play Swimming on Concrete, which was based on the writings of Vassar Miller, was produced in February 2000 at the Theater of the Seventh Sister in Lancaster, Pennsylvania.
Kellner met Vassar Miller in 1974, when he arranged a poetry reading of her work at Millersville. That led to several other readings on various college and university campuses and at the 1978 American Medical Association conference. Kellner and Miller enjoyed a lengthy correspondence, in which Miller offered rare insights into her work, and an intimate friendship.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes correspondence, creative works, clippings, and printed matter written by or related to the poet Vassar Miller. The materials fall between the years 1969 and 2000. Included in this collection are poems and other works by Vassar Miller, critical essays about Vassar Miller, photocopied newspaper clippings, and a typescript of Bruce Kellner's play about Vassar Miller, Swimming on Concrete.
Several folders include correspondence related to Vassar Miller's care in a nursing facility in 1996.
Subjects (Persons)
Miller, Vassar; Kellner, Bruce
Formats
Correspondence; Clippings
Access Restrictions
Open for research. The envelope in Box 1, Folder 7 is closed to the public until after the donor's death.
Acquisition
This collection was donated by Bruce Kellner in November 2000.
Detailed Description
- (Box 1, Folder 1-30)
  - Correspondence from VM, 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from VM, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from VM, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from VM, 1987-ca. 1990s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from VM and JoAnn Avinger, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence from VM and JoAnn Avinger, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sealed Envelope, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    [THIS ITEM TO REMAIN SEALED UNTIL AFTER DONOR'S DEATH]
  - Poems, Unpublished, 1974-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Poems, Unpublished, 1987-1991, and undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Poems, Unpublished, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Works, Autobiography, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Works, Despite This Flesh Introduction, [ca. 1985] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Works about VM, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Critical essays about VM: Terence Doody, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Critical essays about VM: Mary Therese Genovesi, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
  - Critical essays about VM: Paul Christensen, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Critical essays about VM: Marilyn Durfee, May 16, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Critical essays about VM, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence about VM: Nursing Home, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence about VM: Nursing Home, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1998 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Articles, 1969-1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Articles, 1995-2000 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Printed Materials/Memorial Service, 1972-1998 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Publications, 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Struggling to Swim on Concrete Typescript and Program, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Struggling to Swim on Concrete Typescript, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: To Bruce Kellner from Steven Ford Brown, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)